Guide to the Student Volunteer Movement for Foreign Missions Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Organization and Policy Records, Series V
  - Chronological Sequence
    - 1902 SVM Leaders' Conference (Box 449, Folder 5253)
    - 1903: Executive Committee (Box 449, Folder 5254)
    - 1902 SVM Leaders' Conference (Box 449, Folder 5255)
    - 1903-1904: Miscellaneous (Box 449, Folder 5256)
    - 1904: Executive Committee (Box 450, Folder 5257)
    - 1904: SVM Leaders' Conference (Box 450, Folder 5258)
    - 1905: Executive Committee (Box 450, Folder 5259)
    - 1906: Executive Committee (Box 450, Folder 5260)
    - 1906: Miscellaneous (Box 450, Folder 5261)
    - 1907: Executive Committee (Box 450, Folder 5262)
    - : SVM Leaders' Conference (Box 450, Folder 5263)
    - 1908: Executive Committee (Box 450, Folder 5264)
    - 1909; Executive Committee (Box 450, Folder 5265)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 450, Folder 5266)
    - 1910: Executive Committee (Box 450, Folder 5267)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 450, Folder 5268)
    - 1911; Executive Committee (Box 450, Folder 5269)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 450, Folder 5270)
    - 1912: Executive Committee (Box 450, Folder 5271)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 450, Folder 5272)
    - 1913: Executive Committee (Box 450, Folder 5273)
    - 1914: Executive Committee (Box 450, Folder 5274)
    - 1914-1915: Miscellaneous (Box 450, Folder 5275)
    - 1916: Miscellaneous (Box 450, Folder 5276)
    - 1919: Executive Committee (Box 450, Folder 5277)
    - : Standing Committee and Convention Committee (Box 450, Folder 5278)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 450, Folder 5279)
    - 1920: Candidate department (Box 451, Folder 5280)
    - : Educational department (Box 451, Folder 5281)
    - : Standing Committee (Box 451, Folder 5283)
    - : Student Volunteer Council (First) (Box 451, Folder 5284)
    - 1921: Executive Committee (Box 451, Folder 5285)
    - : Standing Committee (Box 451, Folder 5286)
    - : Student Volunteer Council (Second) (Box 451, Folder 5287)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 451, Folder 5288)
    - 1922: Executive Committee (Box 451, Folder 5289)
    - : Standing Committee (Box 451, Folder 5290)
    - : Student Volunteer Council (Third) (Box 451, Folder 5291)
    - 1923: Board of Trustees (Box 451, Folder 5292)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 451, Folder 5293)
    - : Standing Committee (Box 451, Folder 5294)
    - : Student Volunteer Council (Fourth) (Box 452, Folder 5295)
    - 1924: Board of Trustees (Box 452, Folder 5296)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 452, Folder 5297)
    - : Reactions to article written by John L. Childs re. SVM (Box 452, Folder 5298)
    - : Standing Committee: Student Volunteer Council (Fifth -- February) (Box 452, Folder 5299)
    - --Minutes, Delegates list (Box 452, Folder 5300)
    - --Reports, etc. (Box 452, Folder 5301)
    - --Reactions to criticisms: Student Volunteer Council (Sixth -- December) (Box 452, Folder 5302)
    - --Minutes, reports, Round Robins no. 1-3 (Box 453, Folder 5303)
    - --Round Robins no. 4-6 (Box 453, Folder 5304)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 453, Folder 5305)
    - 1925: Commission of Ten on the SVM (Box 453, Folder 5306)
    - : Commission of Ten on the SVM (Box 453, Folder 5307)
    - 1925: Executive Committee (Box 453, Folder 5306)
    - : Standing Committee (Box 453, Folder 5309)
    - 1926: Administrative Committee (Box 453, Folder 5310)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 453, Folder 5311)
    - : General Council (First) (Box 453, Folder 5312)
    - : Standing Committee (Box 453, Folder 5313)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 453, Folder 5314)
    - 1927: Administrative Committee (Box 454, Folder 5315)
    - : Board of Trustees (Box 454, Folder 5316)
    - : Committee on Policy and Program (Box 454, Folder 5317)
    - : General Council (Second) (Box 454, Folder 5318)
    - 1928: Administrative Committee (Box 454, Folder 5319)
    - : Board of Trustees (Box 454, Folder 5320)
    - : General Council (Third) (Box 454, Folder 5321)
    - 1929: Administrative Committee (Box 454, Folder 5322)
    - : General Council (Fourth) (Box 454, Folder 5323)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 454, Folder 5324)
    - 1930: Administrative Committee (Box 454, Folder 5325)
    - : Evaluations of SVM Declaration of Purpose Cards (Box 454, Folder 5326)
    - : General Council (Fifth) (Box 454, Folder 5327)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 454, Folder 5328)
    - 1931: Administrative Committee (Box 455, Folder 5329)
    - : General Council (Sixth) (Box 455, Folder 5330)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 455, Folder 5331)
    - 1932: Administrative Committee (Box 455, Folder 5332)
    - : Fennell P. Turner memorial service (Box 455, Folder 5333)
    - 1932: General Council (Seventh) (Box 455, Folder 5334)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 455, Folder 5335)
    - 1933: Administrative Committee (Box 455, Folder 5336)
    - : Commission to Study the Work of the SVM (Box 455, Folder 5337)
    - : Commission to Study the Work of the SVM (Box 455, Folder 5338)
    - : Commission to Study the Work of the SVM (Box 455, Folder 5339)
    - : General Council (Eighth) (Box 455, Folder 5340)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 455, Folder 5341)
    - 1934: Administrative Committee (Box 456, Folder 5342)
    - : General Council (Ninth) (Box 456, Folder 5343)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 456, Folder 5344)
    - 1935: Administrative Committee (Box 456, Folder 5345)
    - : Advisory Council dinner (Box 456, Folder 5346)
    - : General Council (Tenth) (Box 456, Folder 5347)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 456, Folder 5348)
    - 1936: Administrative Committee (Box 456, Folder 5349)
    - : Board of Trustees (Box 456, Folder 5350)
    - : Commission on Reorganization (Box 456, Folder 5351)
    - : Commission on Reorganization (Box 456, Folder 5352)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 456, Folder 5353)
    - : General Committee (Box 456, Folder 5354)
    - : General Council (Eleventh)--Preparatory Study Course (Box 456, Folder 5355)
    - : General Council (Eleventh)--Correspondence (Box 456, Folder 5356)
    - : General Council (Eleventh)--Mimeographed Correspondence and reports (Box 457, Folder 5357)
    - : General Council (Eleventh)--S. V. Forum and Council minutes and membership (Box 457, Folder 5358)
    - : General Council (Eleventh)--Schedules, etc. (Box 457, Folder 5359)
    - : Jesse R. Wilson Dinner (Box 457, Folder 5360)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 457, Folder 5361)
    - 1937: Board of Trustees (Box 457, Folder 5362)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 457, Folder 5363)
    - : General Committee (Box 457, Folder 5364)
    - : Paul J. Braisted dinner (Box 457, Folder 5365)
    - : Personnel Committee (Box 457, Folder 5366)
    - : Retreats (Box 457, Folder 5367)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 457, Folder 5368)
    - 1938: Board of Trustees (Box 457, Folder 5369)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 457, Folder 5370)
    - : Finance Committee (Box 457, Folder 5371)
    - : General Committee (Box 457, Folder 5372)
    - : Personnel Committee (Box 457, Folder 5373)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 457, Folder 5374)
    - 1939: Executive Committee (Box 458, Folder 5375)
    - : Finance Committee (Box 458, Folder 5376)
    - : General Committee (Box 458, Folder 5377)
    - : Personnel Committee (Box 458, Folder 5378)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 458, Folder 5379)
    - 1940: Administrative Committee (Box 458, Folder 5380)
    - : Board of Trustees (Box 458, Folder 5381)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 458, Folder 5382)
    - 1940: Finance Committee (Box 458, Folder 5383)
    - : General Committee (Box 458, Folder 5384)
    - : Missionary Education Survey (Box 458, Folder 5385)
    - : Personnel Committee (Box 458, Folder 5386)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 458, Folder 5387)
    - 1941: Board of Directors (Box 458, Folder 5388)
    - : Board of Directors (Box 458, Folder 5389)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 458, Folder 5390)
    - : Finance Committee (Box 459, Folder 5391)
    - : Personnel Committee (Box 459, Folder 5392)
    - : Staff retreat -- July (Box 459, Folder 5393)
    - : Staff retreat -- October (Box 459, Folder 5394)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 459, Folder 5395)
    - 1942: Board of Directors (Box 459, Folder 5396)
    - : Board of Directors (Box 459, Folder 5397)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 459, Folder 5398)
    - : Finance Committee (Box 459, Folder 5399)
    - : Personnel Committee (Box 459, Folder 5400)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 459, Folder 5401)
    - 1943: Advisory Council (Box 459, Folder 5402)
    - : Board of Directors (Box 459, Folder 5403)
    - : Board of Directors (Box 459, Folder 5404)
    - : Committee on Christian Reconstruction (Box 460, Folder 5405)
    - : Committee on Christian Reconstruction (Box 460, Folder 5406)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 460, Folder 5407)
    - : Finance Committee (Box 460, Folder 5408)
    - 1943: Personnel Committee (Box 460, Folder 5409)
    - : R. H. Edwin Espy testimonial (Box 460, Folder 5410)
    - : R. H. Edwin Espy replacement search (Box 460, Folder 5411)
    - : Winburn Thomas dinner (Box 460, Folder 5412)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 460, Folder 5413)
    - 1944: Board of Directors (Box 460, Folder 5414)
    - : Board of Directors (Box 460, Folder 5415)
    - : Committee on High School Program (Box 460, Folder 5416)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 460, Folder 5417)
    - : Finance Committee (Box 460, Folder 5418)
    - : Personnel Committee (Box 460, Folder 5419)
    - : Staff training conference (Box 460, Folder 5420)
    - : Summer service program (Box 461, Folder 5421)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 461, Folder 5422)
    - 1945: Board of Directors (Box 461, Folder 5423)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 461, Folder 5424)
    - : Finance Committee (Box 461, Folder 5425)
    - : Personnel Committee (Box 461, Folder 5426)
    - : Staff training conference (Box 461, Folder 5427)
    - : Summer service program (Box 461, Folder 5428)
    - : Summer service program (Box 461, Folder 5429)
    - : Summer service program (Box 461, Folder 5430)
    - : Summer service program (Box 461, Folder 5431)
    - : Summer service program (Box 461, Folder 5432)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 461, Folder 5433)
    - 1946: Board of Directors (Box 462, Folder 5434)
    - : Board of Directors (Box 462, Folder 5435)
    - 1946: Executive Committee (Box 462, Folder 5436)
    - : Finance Committee (Box 462, Folder 5437)
    - : Personnel Committee (Box 462, Folder 5438)
    - : Summer service program (Box 462, Folder 5439)
    - : Summer service program (Box 462, Folder 5440)
    - : Summer service program (Box 462, Folder 5441)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 462, Folder 5442)
    - 1947: Anniversary dinner (Box 462, Folder 5443)
    - : Board of Directors (Box 462, Folder 5444)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 462, Folder 5445)
    - : Finance Committeee (Box 462, Folder 5446)
    - : Personnel Committee (Box 462, Folder 5447)
    - : Special Commission on the Future of the SVM (Roberts Commission) (Box 463, Folder 5448)
    - : Special Commission on the Future of the SVM (Box 463, Folder 5449)
    - : Summer service program (Box 463, Folder 5450)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 463, Folder 5451)
    - 1948: Board of Directors (April) (Box 463, Folder 5452)
    - : Board of Directors (October) (Box 463, Folder 5453)
    - : Committee to prepare study outline for European student missionary conference (Box 463, Folder 5454)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 463, Folder 5455)
    - : Finance Committee (Box 463, Folder 5456)
    - : Luncheon to discuss advance plans (Box 463, Folder 5457)
    - : Personnel Committee (Box 463, Folder 5458)
    - : Property Committee (Box 463, Folder 5459)
    - : Special Commission on Future Policy of the SVM (Roberts Commission) (Box 463, Folder 5460)
    - 1948: Staff training conference (Box 463, Folder 5461)
    - : Winburn Thomas/Edward Johnson dinner (Box 463, Folder 5462)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 463, Folder 5463)
    - 1949: Advisory Council dinner (Box 464, Folder 5464)
    - : Advisory Council dinner (Box 464, Folder 5465)
    - : Board of Directors -- Nominating Committee (Box 464, Folder 5466)
    - : Board of Directors (April) (Box 464, Folder 5467)
    - : Board of Directors (September) (Box 464, Folder 5468)
    - : Board of Directors (Box 464, Folder 5469)
    - : Board of Directors (Box 464, Folder 5470)
    - : Budget and Finance Committee (Box 464, Folder 5471)
    - : Committee to Study the Declaration Card (Box 464, Folder 5472)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 464, Folder 5473)
    - : Personnel Committee (Box 464, Folder 5474)
    - : Policy Committee (Box 464, Folder 5475)
    - : Property Committee (Box 464, Folder 5476)
    - : Staff meetings (Box 464, Folder 5477)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 465, Folder 5478)
    - 1950: Advisory Council dinner (Box 465, Folder 5479)
    - : Advisory Council dinner (Box 465, Folder 5480)
    - : Board of Directors and Corporation (April) (Box 465, Folder 5481)
    - : Board of Directors (September) (Box 465, Folder 5482)
    - : Board of Directors (Box 465, Folder 5483)
    - : Board of Directors (Box 465, Folder 5484)
    - : Board of Directors -- Nominating Committee (Box 465, Folder 5485)
    - :Budget and Finance Committee (Box 465, Folder 5486)
    - 1950: executive Committee (Box 465, Folder 5487)
    - : Personnel Committee (Box 466, Folder 5488)
    - : Policy Committee (Box 466, Folder 5489)
    - : Property Committee (Box 466, Folder 5490)
    - : Staff meetings (Box 466, Folder 5491)
    - : Staff training conference (Box 466, Folder 5492)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 466, Folder 5493)
    - 1951: Board of Directors (April) (Box 466, Folder 5494)
    - : Board of Directors (Box 466, Folder 5495)
    - : Board of Directors (Box 466, Folder 5496)
    - : Board of Directors Nominating Committee (Box 466, Folder 5497)
    - : Budget and Finance Committee (Box 466, Folder 5498)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 466, Folder 5499)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 467, Folder 5500)
    - : Personnel Committee (Box 467, Folder 5501)
    - : Staff meetings (Box 467, Folder 5502)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 467, Folder 5503)
    - 1952: Board of Directors and Corporation (April) (Box 467, Folder 5504)
    - : Board of Directors (September) Pre-Board Student Conference (Box 467, Folder 5505)
    - : Board of Directors (September) (Box 467, Folder 5506)
    - : Board of Directors (Box 467, Folder 5507)
    - : Board of Directors Nominating Committee (Box 467, Folder 5508)
    - : Budget and Finance Committee (Box 467, Folder 5509)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 467, Folder 5510)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 467, Folder 5511)
    - 1952: Personnel Committee (Box 468, Folder 5512)
    - : Policy Committee (Box 468, Folder 5513)
    - : Staff briefing conference (Box 468, Folder 5514)
    - : Staff meetings (Box 468, Folder 5515)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 468, Folder 5516)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 468, Folder 5517)
    - 1953: Board of Directors (April) (Box 468, Folder 5518)
    - : Board of Directors (September) (Box 468, Folder 5519)
    - : Board of Directors (September) (Box 468, Folder 5520)
    - : Board of Directors (Box 468, Folder 5521)
    - : Board of Directors Nominating Committee (Box 468, Folder 5522)
    - 1953: Budget and Finance Committee (Box 469, Folder 5523)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 469, Folder 5524)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 469, Folder 5525)
    - : Personnel Committee (Box 469, Folder 5526)
    - : Policy Committee (Box 469, Folder 5527)
    - : Special Committee to Consult re. SVM-NCCC (Box 469, Folder 5528)
    - : Staff meetings (Box 469, Folder 5529)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 469, Folder 5530)
    - 1954: Board of Directors (Box 469, Folder 5531)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 469, Folder 5532)
    - : Personnel Committee (Box 469, Folder 5533)
    - : Staff Briefing conference (Box 469, Folder 5534)
    - : Staff meetings (Box 469, Folder 5535)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 470, Folder 5536)
    - 1955: Board of Directors (Box 470, Folder 5537)
    - 1955: Budget and Finance Committee (Box 470, Folder 5538)
    - : Personnel Committee (Box 470, Folder 5539)
    - : Staff meetings (Box 470, Folder 5540)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 470, Folder 5541)
    - 1956: Board of Directors (Box 470, Folder 5542)
    - : Budget and Finance Committee (Box 470, Folder 5543)
    - : Executive Committee (Box 470, Folder 5544)
    - : Personnel Committee (Box 470, Folder 5545)
    - : Policy Committee (Box 470, Folder 5546)
    - : Staff meetings (Box 470, Folder 5547)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 470, Folder 5548)
    - 1957: Executive Committee (Box 470, Folder 5549)
    - : Staff meetings (Box 470, Folder 5550)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 470, Folder 5551)
    - 1958: Consultation on Philosophy of Education for Missionary Enlistment (Box 470, Folder 5552)
    - : Miscellaneous (Box 470, Folder 5553)
    - 1959: Board of Directors, SVM Corporation (Box 470, Folder 5554)
    - 1959: National Student Christian Federation Commission on World Mission (Box 470, Folder 5554)
    - 1960: National Student Christian Federation Commission on World Mission (Box 470, Folder 5555)
    - 1961: National Student Christian-Federation Commission on World Mission (Box 470, Folder 5556)
    - 1962: National Student Christian Federation Commission on World Mission (Box 470, Folder 5557)
    - Undated material (Box 470, Folder 5558)
    - Undated material (Box 471, Folder 5559-5561)
  - Topical Sequence
    - Material related to Student Volunteer Movement watchword, 1896-1909 (Box 471, Folder 5562)
    - Material related to Student Volunteer Movement watchword, 1912-1916 (Box 471, Folder 5563)
    - Material related to Student Volunteer Movement watchword, n.d. (Box 471, Folder 5564)
    - Material related to race questions in missions, 1920-1929 (Box 471, Folder 5565)
    - Material related to race questions in missions, 1930-1952 (Box 471, Folder 5566)
    - Material related to race questions in missions, 1934-1953 (Box 471, Folder 5567)
    - Material related to race questions in missions, 1958 (Box 471, Folder 5568)
- Field Work, Series VI
  From the 1886 Wilder-Forman deputation to the cooperative ventures in the late 1950s, the Student Volunteer Movement consistently viewed field work as the most important part of its program. The aim of field work was to develop missionary enthusiasm and thereby recruit volunteers, to educate regarding missionary concerns, to establish continuing student volunteer fellowships, and to promote the quadrennial conventions. Series VI contains over twenty linear feet of material and is divided into three sections.
  A. General field work
  The records in this topically arranged section include annual reports and statistics, form letters, procedural instructions and publicity releases. Of particular interest is a series of volumes which are compilations of very specific information regarding campus visits during the period 1909 to 1931. These volumes provide valuable documentation of the state of religious life on American campuses during this period.
  B. Field staff recruitment
  The chronologically arranged correspondence of this section dates from 1930 to 1955 and concerns the recruitment of traveling secretaries. The SVM's traveling secretaries were primarily recently graduated volunteers not yet gone to the field or missionaries home on furlough. Many letters were exchanged with denominational boards in the effort to obtain personnel and financial support for the SVM field work program.
  C. Traveling secretary correspondence
  Following two folders of general material, the correspondence in this section is arranged alphabetically by the names of the traveling secretaries. The correspondence dates from the early 1900s to the late 1950s and includes letters exchanged between the secretaries and SVM headquarters, as well as letters concerning local arrangements for visits, itinerary planning sheets, and publicity releases regarding specific secretaries. In some cases the files of correspondence include letters from before and after the traveling secretary's term of service.
  D. Traveling secretary reports The reports in this section are of three types:
  1. Monthly reports: During the early years of the Movement traveling secretaries filled out forms describing their activities on a monthly basis. These monthly statements are available only for the
  periods 1897 to 189S, 1927 to 1929, and 1931 to 1933, but the information which would have been found on the forms was largely entered into the record books of section A of this Series. The monthly reports are arranged by year and alphabetically by the name of the secretary within the year.
  2. Financial reports: A small section of traveling secretary financial reports covers the period 1930 to 1942 and contains records of expenses.
  3. Campus visit reports: Of most interest are the reports submitted by traveling secretaries concerning their visits to specific campuses throughout the United States. These reports have varying formats but generally contain information regarding the activities of the secretary during his or her visit and the state of student missionary interest at the institution. The campus visit reports date from 1928 to the late 1950s and provide valuable information regarding religious conditions on American campuses. They are arranged in two sequences,one dating from approximately 1928 to 1933, and the other dating from 1933 to the late 1950s. The reports are arranged alphabetically by state and within each state by the name of the institution visited.
  E. Records of student volunteer unions and groups
  According to Student Volunteer Movement policy, individuals were first and foremost members of the national Movement, but local volunteer "groups" (formerly called "bands") and regional volunteer "unions" were found to be effective means for providing fellowship and support for volunteers. From the earliest days of the SVM, relationships between the national Movement and its local and regional expressions were often a problem. Local groups tended to gradually lose contact with the aims and mood of the national headquarters and to settle into their own traditions. Some groups, for example, became involved in home missions projects at a time when the national Movement was striving to confirm its commitment to the foreign side of missions.
  Relatively little mention is made of student volunteer unions and groups in the annual reports of the SVM General Secretaries before the 1920s. The Movement was anxious not to appear as a rival to the YMCA and YWCA groups on campuses. When the organizational arrangement of the Movement was changed in 1920 to allow for more student participation, the student volunteer unions became somewhat more important because the student members of the new General Council were to be elected by the regional unions. In 1936 the Movement changed its policy on local volunteer groups, recommending that they no longer exist as autonomous organizations but rather incorporate their activities into other religious organizations on campus. It was not until 1947 that this policy was reversed.
  The material in this section dates from l892 to 1954. Preceding the material which relates to specific regional, state, or city unions are three records books and several folders of general material including manuals with suggested procedures for student volunteer groups and unions. Also included in this first section are materials related to the campus representative system which the SVM experimented with in 1945 and materials related to a 1933 survey on 'missionary interest in the colleges." Records of local groups, such as a 1903 minute book of the Bryn Mawr College Student Volunteer Band, are not listed separately in this section, but rather will be found amidst the regional, state, or city union records.